Good morning this is Dan Margolies filling in for Rabbi Linzer. We're
on the top of דף מ"ג עמוד א' Daf Mem Gimmel Amud
Aleph right at the new משנה mishnah and we have a jam
packed דף daf with all sorts of wonderful new things. We're getting
close to the end of פרק המפקיד, Perek Hamapkid, we may finish
it today, we may not, depends on how time goes. The משנה
mishnah says: המפקיד מעות אצל שולחני, Hamapkid maot eitzel shulchani, if you
give money to a שולחני, shulchani, a money changer, אם צרורים, im
tzerurim, if they are bound up together in a leather pouch, לא
ישתמש בהם, lo yishtamesh bahem, then the שולחני shulchani cannot use them.
לפיכך אם אבדו אינו חייב באחריותן, Lefichach im avdu eino chayav beachrayutam,
therefore if the שולחני shulchani loses them, then he is not חייב
chayav for their liability because he was basically like a שומר חינם.
shomer chinam. That is you gave it to him to watch, but
נו nu he doesn't have that much liability. מותרים, Mutarim, if they
are unbound, that is you gave a sack of coins to him,
ישתמש בהם, yishtamesh bahem, then he could use them. לפיכך אם אבדו
חייב באחריותם, Lefichach im avdu chayav beachrayutam, but if they get lost
then he is חייב באחריותם. chayav beachrayutam.
Even if he hasn't used them?
We're going to see in the גמרא Gemara it's a question whether
or not it kicks in at the time he uses them or
even before that, that's a persistent question in the laws of שואל,
shoel, that is the highest liability of a שואל, shoel, that is
you're allowed to use it but you're חייב chayav even באונס be'oness
and things like that. Does that only kick in at the time
that you used it or does it even kick in before you
used it? And תוספות Tosafot makes a lot of points about that
and the ריטב"א Ritva makes a number of points about that about
when does that חיוב chiyuv kick in? But that's a major topic
for this דף daf in, you know, in the ראשונים. Rishonim. So
but the alternative, אצל בעל הבית, eitzel ba'al habayit, if you give
it to just a regular person, a regular homeowner, בין צרורים, bein
tzerurim, whether they are bound up, בין מותרים, bein mutarim, if they
are unbound, לא ישתמש בהם, lo yishtamesh bahem, then a householder can't
use them. לפיכך אם אבדו אינו חייב באחריותן, Lefichach im avdu eino
chayav beachrayutam, because if you gave it to your friend, then that's
just automatically normal שומר חינם. shomer chinam. In other words, it sounds
like here if you had an unspoken agreement with this שולחני, shulchani,
the assumption is that when you give it to him unbound, he's
not a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, he's actually either a שומר שכר
shomer sachar or a שואל, shoel, and that's going to be a
מחלוקת machloket in the גמרא Gemara as well. But the point is
that because you gave it to him in the customary way, it's
unbound, he's a money changer, his job is to use the money,
so the assumption was that you wanted him to be some other
kind of שומר, shomer, to have a higher level liability but with
the right to use it. Yeah?
You said putting it in a leather pouch, I always had the
image that they kept coins in like a cloth that they knotted,
they put their coins and then they knotted it and that was
a צרור. tzror. Is that?
So צרור המעות, tzror hamot, the משנה mishnah in כלים Kelim talks
about a צרור המעות tzror hamot is טהור tahor but a צרור
המרגלית tzror hamargalit is טמא. tamei. Why?
Because a צרור המעות tzror
hamot is not a כלי kli because it's a flat piece of
leather that is continuously bound and unbound, you always are opening and
closing your wallet, so it's never, the leather never conforms to the
shape of the coin. But צרור המרגלית, tzror hamargalit, you put your
jewels in there and wrap it up and leave it there for
ten years, it'll conform to the shape of the jewels, so that'll
be a כלי, kli, so that's why that would be טמא. tamei.
וצרת הכסף, Vetzarta hakesef, so the many of the cases in the
משנה mishnah in talking about that discuss this צרור. tzror. It's basically
a wallet, that's how you have to think about it, it's in
the wallet. You give your wallet to the שולחני, shulchani, the coins
are in there, well that means you want him to be a
שומר shomer just to watch it. If you give him a stack
of bills, that's an assumption that he's going to be interchangeable the
bills or the coins. Okay, so and the final statement in the
משנה: mishnah: חנוני כבעל הבית, Chanvani keba'al habayit,
a shopkeeper, a store owner, someone who sells things is like a
בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, if asking someone a friend to watch it,
there's no assumption that he'll be able allowed to use the money.
דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, that's Rabbi Meir's opinion. רבי יהודה
אומר חנוני כשולחני. Rabbi Yehuda omer chanvani keshulchani. According to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, a חנוני, chanvani, a shopkeeper, is like a שולחני shulchani
because there's an assumption that the shopkeeper also would want the rights
to be able to use the money, and that's more, I think
this is more of a question just about what are the commercial
standards in that area as far as I can see. I don't
see a real conceptual distinction between Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehuda, obviously
analysis of what those roles were like at the time is very
important to understand these kinds of things. So the גמרא Gemara says:
משום דצרורים לא ישתמש בהם? Mishum detzerurim lo yishtamesh bahem? So what,
because they are bound up, that's why he's not allowed to use
them? אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi
Yehuda, בצרורים וחתומים שנו. betzerurim vechatumim shanu. No, it must be that
they were not only bound up, but there was a signet, a
seal placed on the binding to say don't open it. That is
even if you give your wallet to the שולחני, shulchani, the assumption
would be that he would be allowed to use it.
Why? I mean, I don't know, it seems to me, seems reasonable
wouldn't you assume so if you were a שולחני? shulchani?
Yeah, I mean like what... so but what גילוי דעת giluy da'at
did you give that allows him one way or the other to
know? You gave it to a שולחני, shulchani, שולחני's shulchani job is
to change the money, okay, so he could use the money.
Because you didn't give him his money, you gave him a wallet.
But now remember, giving him money means a higher level liability but
also he's going to be allowed to use it. So that's the
question. Think of it as like giving your money to the bank.
When you give your money to the bank it's basically a loan
for the bank to be able to invest the money somewhere else.
So that's something to think about here as well. ואמר רבי אסי
אמר רבי יהודה בצרורים וחתומים שנו. Ve'amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yehuda
betzerurim vechatumim shanu. So they said it was that there was actually
a seal on the binding of the wallet. רב מרי אמר: Rav
Mari amar: בקשר משונה. bekesher meshuneh.
So רב מרי Rav Mari says it must be that the, or
alternatively or perhaps differently, the knot has to be a unique knot.
We saw this already back in אלו מציאות Eilu Metzios that certain
things get tied with a personal knot, a סימן, siman, some kind
of a סימן, siman, but that also signifies the person
does not want the שליח shaliach to use the money. איכא דאמרי
Ika d'amri there's a different version of רב מרי's Rav Mari opinion.
בעא Ba'i רב מרי Rav Mari קשר משונה. kesher meshune. So not
that רב מרי Rav Mari stated the הלכה halacha but actually that
רב מרי Rav Mari asked the question. What do we say about
a קשר משונה? kesher meshune? מאי? Mai? And the answer was תיקו.
teiku. So רב מרי Rav Mari maybe is an unresolved opinion or
maybe stated it as authoritatively. We know that
in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, I think it's on דף ט, daf
tes, but I could be wrong about the דף, daf, there's a
תוספות Tosafot with four different opinions about what איכא דאמרי ika d'amri
means and how do we פסקן pasken the הלכה halacha in each
of those cases. עיין שם. Ayin sham. Okay. מותרין ישתמש בהן. Mutarin
yishtamesh bahem.
Basically we're really seeing this is
a very specific case. He's always allowed to use them.
Which means then he's basically always allowed to use them unless, right,
so the question we're going to get into now is what kind
of a שומר shomer is the שולחני? shulchani? What kind of agreement,
if he's a שומר שכר shomer sachar then what kind of שכר
sachar is he getting out of it? And if he's a שואל,
shoel, so obviously it's going to have an even higher level of
liability. מותרין ישתמש בהן. Mutarin yishtamesh bahem.
If they are unbound, that is it's an open wallet.
שומר שכר, shomer sachar, that's what it
says, אם אבדו im avdu it's... We're going to see. It's a
מחלוקת אמוראים. machlokes amoraim. So we're going to see it right now.
מותרין ישתמש בהן. Mutarin yishtamesh bahem. If it's open, then he is
allowed to use them. אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna ואפילו נאנסו.
v'afillu ne'ensu. רב הונא Rav Huna says even באונס. b'ones. That is
the שולחני shulchani is considered with the liabilities of a שואל. shoel.
Okay. והא אבדו קתני, Ve'ha avdu katani, but the משנה mishnah says
אבדו, avdu, they got lost, which would not imply that he's a
שואל, shoel, only that he's a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. כדרבה, Kid'Rabba,
so he must say קתני כדרבה. katani kid'Rabba. רב הונא Rav Huna
must read the משנה mishnah like רבה. Rabba. דאמר רבה De'amar Rabba
נגנבו בלסטים מזויין nignevu b'listim mezuyan אבדו כשתבעה ספינתו בים. avdu kesheteva
sefinato bayam. We saw this multiple times that רבה Rabba in a
number of cases will read the case of theft not as theft
that a שומר שכר shomer sachar would be חייב chayav for but
a שומר חנם shomer chinam would be פטור pattur for, but actually
is ליסטים מזויין, listim mezuyan, that is armed robbery. Armed robbery even
a שומר שכר shomer sachar is פטור. pattur. And אבדו, avdu, אבדו
avdu doesn't mean that it got lost that a שומר שכר shomer
sachar would be חייב. chayav. אבדו avdu means a case of real
אונס, ones, getting lost like the ship sank in the ocean. רב
נחמן אמר נאנסו לא. Rav Nachman amar ne'ensu lo. רב נחמן Rav
Nachman says no, if it was באונס, b'ones, then the שולחני shulchani
is not חייב. chayav. So the שולחני shulchani should be considered not
like a שואל, shoel, but like a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Okay.
אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava le'Rav Nachman, so רבא
Rava challenged רב נחמן's Rav Nachman opinion. לדידך דאמרת נאנסו לא, L'didach
d'amart ne'ensu lo, you said if it doesn't apply in a case
of אונס, ones, אלמא לא הוי שואל עלייהו. alma lo havei shoel
aleihu. So then you should say that he's not a שואל. shoel.
So that makes sense because obviously the liability is more comparable to
שומר שכר. shomer sachar. ואי שואל לא הוי, Ve'ee shoel lo havei,
if he's not a שואל, shoel, שומר שכר נמי לא הוי. shomer
sachar nami lo havei. So then he's also not a שומר שכר.
shomer sachar. Meaning logically, according to רבא's Rava question, the point is
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, שואל shoel I understand, you gave it to
him and he has the right to use it. That would make
sense in this context. But what שומר שכר shomer sachar is he
to watch it but he's getting paid? What is he getting paid
for to watch it even if he's not allowed to use it?
That's the question. אמר ליה, Amar lei, רב נחמן Rav Nachman responds,
בהא מודינא לך be'ha modina lach דהואיל ונהנה ממנה de'ho'il venehene mimena
בההיא הנאה behahi hana'ah דאי מיתרמי ליה זבינא דאית בה רווחא זבין
בהו de'ee mitrami lei zabina de'is ba ravcha zavin behu הוי עליהו
שומר שכר. havei aleihu shomer sachar. So according to רב נחמן's Rav
Nachman answer he says no, he is a שומר שכר. shomer sachar.
It's similar perhaps to the case we've seen of פרוטה דרב יוסף
pruta de'Rav Yosef in a kind of reverse. In this case the
שומר shomer while watching the money, if a really good deal comes
along he's allowed to tap into those funds to
purchase at a low price and then he can pay it back
later. So that's he is allowed to use the money in extenuating
circumstance and that's and even then.
I mean just the fact he gets to use it just every
day you know it's a value. He doesn't have to go to
the bank.
No but he said לא ישתמש בהן, lo yishtamesh bahem, right? Sorry,
ישתמש בהן, yishtamesh bahem, he is allowed to use them.
Right. Point. He's allowed to use it in the course of business,
that itself is a הנאה.
hana'ah. But there's no real הנאה hana'ah to be able to spend
the money. All he does he gives a ten dollar bill and
gets ten one dollar
bills. But you're a שולחני shulchani so that's your job, you don't
have it there is no הנאה hana'ah in exchanging money of equal
value in this context. It's easier. It's easier. Okay. So that's why
there's such a thing as a שולחני. shulchani. But it doesn't mean
that there's a real monetary הנאה. hana'ah. Here he has a monetary
benefit in that he's actually able to spend the money.
Otherwise and if he doesn't then he gets no benefit. Right. Exactly.
So if he does then he always has the benefit.
Well that's the question.
איתיביה רב נחמן לרב הונא. Eitivei Rav Nachman le'Rav Huna. So רב
נחמן Rav Nachman is now going to challenge רב הונא's Rav Huna
position. רב הונא Rav Huna remember said he's like a שואל, shoel,
he's חייב chayav even באונס. b'ones. המפקיד מעות אצל שולחני, Hamaphkid ma'os
etzel shulchani, if you give your money to a שולחני, shulchani, so
this is a תוספתא Tosefta from מסכת מעילה Masechet Meilah that has
a similar but different case. It's very similar in structure but it's
talking about if a גזבר gizbar of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
takes הקדש hekdesh money and gives it to a שולחני shulchani by
accident. So המפקיד מעות אצל שולחני, hamaphkid ma'os etzel shulchani, if the
גזבר gizbar gave the money to the שולחני, shulchani, אם צרורין לא
ישתמש בהן. im tzururin lo yishtamesh bahem. So if they were bound
up, then the שולחני shulchani should not use them. Therefore if the
שולחני shulchani did use them, אם הוציא לא מעל הגזבר. im hotzi
lo ma'al hagizbar. Then if the שולחני shulchani took out the money
to use. interchanging the coins, then the גזבר Gizbar is not liable
for מעילה Me'ilah because the only one who did something wrong was
the שולחני. shulchani. That is, the גזבר Gizbar was by mistake, he
accidentally gave the money over, so he's not חייב chayav for מעילה.
Me'ilah. ואם הם מותרים ve-im hem mutarim ישתמש בהם. yishtamesh bahem. And
if they were unbound, then the assumption of the שולחני shulchani is
that he should be allowed to use them. לפיכך, Lefichach, אם הוציא
im hotzi מעל הגזבר. ma'al ha-Gizbar. Then if the שולחני shulchani takes
out the coins, then the גזבר Gizbar has committed a case of
מעילה. Me'ilah.
It was all
accidentally.
The הפקדה, hafkadah, he gave the money intentionally, but he didn't remember
that it was the הקדש hekdesh money. He got mixed up. So
here the question is, like Michael was saying earlier, at what point
do these liabilities kick in? Here it sounds like the liability kicks
in only at the time that the שולחני shulchani takes out the
money. אם הוציא, Im hotzi, if he took out the money. ואם
תאמר Ve-im tomar אפילו נאנסו, afilu ne'ensu, so if you're going to
tell me that you're חייב chayav even באונס, be-ones, that he's like
a שואל, sho'el, says רב נחמן Rav Nachman to רב הונא, Rav
Huna, מאי איריא mai irya הוציא? hotzi? אפילו לא הוציא נמי. afilu
lo hotzi nami. So why does it say whether or not he
took it out? Even if he didn't take it out, because the
liability because why? Because the liability of the שואל sho'el would kick
in according to רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's assumption at the time that
the coins were given over. And if you gave it over and
he has the right to use it, then it's מעילה Me'ilah whether
or not he actually took them out. אמר ליה, Amar leh, הוא
הדין אף על גב דלא הוציא. Hu ha-din af al gav de-lo
hotzi. No, according to רב הונא, Rav Huna, it would apply even
if he didn't, sorry that's part of the question right? אפילו הוציא
נמי. afilu hotzi nami. אמר ליה, Amar leh, הוא הדין. hu ha-din
Right, that's רב הונא'ס Rav Huna's response. הוא הדין hu ha-din. אף
על גב דלא הוציא. af al gav de-lo hotzi. He says even
if he didn't take out the coins, it's still מעילה. Me'ilah. ואיידי
דתנא רישא ve-aidi di-tna reisha הוציא, hotzi, תנא סיפא נמי tna seifa
nami הוציא. hotzi. Alternatively, you just read the משנה, mishnah, the sense
is the משנה mishnah uses a structural form to use the word
הוציא, hotzi, don't have to be מדייק medayek in that use of
the word to say that it means דוקא davka when he took
it out. It would also be שואל. sho'el.
Exactly. He's saying it's like a literary term.
Right. So very often you see this kind of thing. One אמורא,
Amora, one תנא Tanna picks up on a subtlety in the language
and another says, נו, nu, I don't have to hold like that
precision, such precision in the language of the משנה mishnah because the
משנה mishnah would have used that word for a different reason, in
this case using it for the reason to have a parallel structure.
You mean we don't know then when the liability kicks in?
The liability kicks in, that's where all these ראשונים Rishonim talk about
it, it becomes a major question in the ראשונים. Rishonim.
What we said. I'm asking you.
It's a big מחלוקת. machlokes.
So meaning like it can go either way. There is no פסק
psak you're saying.
I don't know פסק psak in שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, I know
that it's a big מחלוקת machlokes in the ראשונים. Rishonim. It is
a big
deal
if they want to borrow my car. Yeah.
If you borrowed it but you didn't drive it out yet, right,
exactly. Well that's going to be touched on in this next סוגיא
sugya as well. Okay. The next משנה mishnah says השולח יד בפיקדון.
Ha-sholeiach yad be-pikadon. Someone who is a שומר shomer watching the פיקדון
pikadon and he goes and steals it. בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai
omrim ילקה בחסר וביתר. yelkeh be-chaser u-be-yeser. He loses out, he will
get hit with, that is, he suffers the loss if it loses
value וביתר u-be-yeser and if it gained value. That is, according to
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, the שומר shomer always gets the lesser of
two options. If it went down in value, he has to pay
back the higher value, and if it went up in value, he
has to pay back again the lower value, the value before it
appreciated. That's what בית שמאי Beis Shammai say. Because the שומר shomer
who was שולח בו יד, sholeiach bo yad, he should get the
short end of the stick, it was his fault, he was פושע.
poshea. ובית הלל אומרים U-Beis Hillel omrim כשעת הוצאה. ki-sh'as hotza'ah. בית
הלל Beis Hillel says it goes, it's assessed at the time of
הוצאה. hotza'ah. We don't know exactly what that הוצאה hotza'ah means, it's
going to be discussed in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי עקיבא אומר כשעת
התביעה. Rabbi Akiva omer ke'sha'as hatviah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it
goes by the time assessed in court. This should recall the discussion
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma in פרק מרובה. Perek Merubah. We saw
the whole discussion there about גניבה וגזילה, gneivah u-gezeilah, when do you
assess כפל kefel and when do you assess ארבעה וחמישה arba'ah va-chamishah
based on the time of the theft or the time of going
to court. So this is a very similar kind of case and
here we have the case of רבא, Rava, a case that is
quoted a few other places in ש"ס, Shas, בבא קמא Bava Kamma
etc. becomes a major question regarding exactly those questions.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, שולח יד sholeiach yad means
a שומר shomer violated the terms of the שמירה shmirah to claim
the object. We're going to see the next משנה'ס mishnah's going to
discuss שליחות יד shlichus yad a little bit more precisely, but basically
you went to, someone gave you a barrel of wine, you're going
to drink a glass of the wine. Someone gave you a pile
of wheat to watch, you took the wheat and ground it to
bake bread or something like that. You stole something from what you
were supposed to be watching.
Or what about like we had this sort of yesterday, let's say
you moved the barrel of wine, didn't take the wine but stood
on the barrel of wine.
Right. You use it in some kind of a way. So those
other kinds of things could also be שליחות יד shlichus yad as
well depending, and we're going to see it's מחלוקת machlokes whether שליחות
יד shlichus yad בעי חסרון ba'ei chisron or not. Does שליחות יד
shlichus yad have to involve a depreciation in the value of the
פיקדון pikadon or not? That is, if you used it in a
way that doesn't devalue it, maybe it's not שליחות יד. shlichus yad.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רבא Rava says האי מאן דגזל חביתא דחמרא
מחבריה, hai man di-gzal chavita de-chamra me-chaverei, someone stole a barrel of
wine from his friend. מעיקרא שויא זוזא, Me-ikara shavei zuza, at first
it was worth one זוז. zuz. השתא שויא ארבעה, Hashta shavei arba'ah,
and now it, price went up after he stole it, now it's
worth four זוז. zuz. תברה או שתייה, Tavrah o shatyei, if he
broke it or drank it, משלם ארבעה. meshaleim arba'ah. Then he pays
four. He has to pay back... back the value at the time
that he broke it or drank it. איטבר ממילא, Itbar mimeila, if
it broke on its own, משלם זוזא, Meshalem zuza, he only pays
one זוז. zuz. Now the interesting question is here don't we say
that a גנב ganav and a גזלן gazlan are חייב chayav even
in case of אונס? oness? So if it broke on its own,
isn't it אונס? oness? Shouldn't we assess it at the time that
it broke? The basic answer is that no, you should assess it
based on the actions of the גנב ganav or the גזלן. gazlan.
That is, the only thing that the person did was to steal
it. So the only time point that we can calculate anything is
the time that he stole it. But in the case where he
drank it or broke it on his own, he took an action,
so taking that action becomes a time point that we can calculate
the value of the barrel at that time and that's why that
would kick in for four, but in the case where it broke
on its own, there's no other time point for his liability, for
his liability. Obviously the time that it broke is relevant to the
barrel, but in terms of the גנב's ganav liability, the גנב ganav
didn't do anything at that time. It's a major discussion in אחרונים,
Achronim, who cares, that's a good question. Okay. You know what I'm
saying?
I understand that.
No, so that's that's part of the question is how do you
understand this סוגיא, sugya, it's a classic סוגיא, sugya, it's very rich.
Okay. So מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? כיוון דאי איתא
הדרא למרה בעינא ההיא שעתא דקא שתי לה או דקא תבר לה
קא גזל מיניה. Keivan de'i ita hadra lemareih be'eina hahi sha'ata deka
shati lah o deka tavar lah ka gazal mineih. So because at
the time that it was after it was stolen, the object is
still present. So if the owner would have claimed it from you
it would always just return the object itself. You could say הרי
שלך לפניך. Harei shelcha lefanecha. But at the time that you went
and broke it or drank it, it transfers into a case of
assessing the value and that value will be assessed at that time.
That is, from when you broke it or
the time when you return it. At the time that you broke
it or drank it presumably. Because that was the time where it
shifted.
Broke it in November you stole it in October you broke it
in November and they want it back in June you're saying
I would pay based on November time. You calculate it based on
the time that you took that action.
Because as you see here, right, the first possibility is you could
just return the object itself, which is always preferable, but in that
case then the owner will suffer the change in value. Here, once
it was broken once you broke it or drank it, then the
גנב ganav claim the liability for the change in value. The גזלן
gazlan sorry, הגזלן hagazlan claims the liability for the change in value.
ותנן כל הגזלנים משלמין כשעת הגזילה. Utnan kol hagazlanim meshalmin kish'at hagezeila.
And we have the ברייתא braita says, the משנה mishna says,
the גזלנים gazlanim pay by the time that they steal it. So
איטבר ממילא משלם זוזא, Itbar mimeila meshalem zuza, so the fact that
you pay if it broke on its own you only pay one
זוז. zuz. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, השתא לא עביד ולא מידי, Hashta
lo avid velo midi, you didn't do anything. In other words, the
גזלן gazlan didn't do anything to click in a new time point
for assessing the value. So אמאי קמיחייב ליה ההיא שעתא דגזילה ההיא
שעתא זוזא הוה שויא. Amai kamichayev leih hahi sha'ata degezeila hahi sha'ata
zuza hava shavya. So at what time can you calculate it well
you can calculate it based on the time that he stole it
and at that time it was only worth one זוז. zuz.
Assuming that he needs to do something, you know what I'm saying.
Okay, so that exactly becomes a lynchpin of this מחלוקת machlokes and
it becomes a major סוגיא sugya discussed by the קצות Ketzos as
discussed by the נתיבות Nesivos it becomes a major major סוגיא sugya
in terms of גזילה gezeila in general, in terms of ownership in
general, in terms of all sorts of things, the fact that basically,
you know, what are we talking about? We're talking about you had
to take some kind of an action. It sounds like here.
Do we follow something or is there still no is it still?
פסקינן Paskinan like yeah, this is an open open רבא Rava right
here. Nobody disagrees with רבא. Rava.
Well no, because there's the other one is כשעת תביעה, Kish'at tveiah,
that's the other way or.
No, but רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but that's Rabbi so the point
is that this סוגיא sugya is about a case of גזילה. gezeila.
The case of גזילה gezeila for sure we have רבא. Rava. The
question is how do we base the משנה, mishna, we're going to
see the the conclusion of the משנה mishna is coming up on
the next דף, daf, on the next עמוד. amud. Okay. תנן ב"ה
אומרים כשעת הוצאה. Tnan Beis Hillel omrim kish'at hotza'ah.
So the משנה mishna says בית הלל Beis Hillel says that in
a case of שליחות יד, shlichut yad, you go by שעת הוצאה.
sh'at hotza'ah. So what is הוצאה? hotza'ah? Okay. מאי כשעת הוצאה אילימא
כשעת הוצאה מן העולם. Mai kish'at hotza'ah eileima kish'at hotza'ah min ha'olam.
The time you took it out of the world, that is it
was consumed. ובמאי אי בחסר מי איכא למאן דאמר והתנן כל הגזלנים
משלמין כשעת הגזילה. Uvemai i bechasar mi ika leman de'amar vehatanun kol
hagazlanim meshalmin kish'at hagezeila.
So you could say that, so what about the depreciation in value
that happens later? Well then you say no, the גזלנים gazlanim pay
at the time of the theft. That is you drank the wine
and then something happened to the value later or something like that,
we don't care because you pay by now. That would be one
way to read it. ואי ביתר היינו ב"ש. Ve'i beyeter hainu Beis
Shammai. But in the case where it increased in value, well then
the
שומר shomeir will not have to pay will still pay the lower
value because he goes by the time that he drank it and
not by the later time. So you kind of misses out on
on that point. אלא פשיטא כשעת הוצאה מבית בעלים. Ela pshita kish'at
hotza'ah mibeis be'alim.
No, it's not when you took it out of the world, it's
when you took it out of the domain, the ownership of the
owners. That is not when it was consumed but when it was
stolen. So לימא רבא דאמר כבית שמאי. Leima Rava de'amar keBeis Shammai.
Well not when stolen, when it was actually taken sorry, when it
was taken into the entrust of the שומר. shomeir. That is when
the שומר shomeir starts watching it in his house, it's no longer
in the
owner's רשות. reshut. לימא רבא דאמר כב"ש, Leima Rava de'amar keBeis Shammai,
but then you're telling me that רבא's Rava opinion, that is that
we just read that ברייתא braita that. מימרא Memra of רבה Rabbah
about תבר ושתי, Tavar v'Shasi, so does רבה Rabbah hold like בית
שמאי? Beis Shamai? אמר לך רבה ביתר כולי האי לא פליגי, Amar
lach Rabbah b'yeter kulei hai lo pligi, כולי
עלמא לא פליגי, kulei alma lo pligi, כי פליגי בחסר.
ki pligi b'chaser. No,
the מחלוקת machlokes is only about if the object went down in
value. בית שמאי סברי... Beis Shamai savri...
Wait, so if it went up in value then what?
So כולי עלמא לא פליגי kulei alma lo pligi that if it
went up in value the thief pays back the higher value because
the point is that the שומר shomer always has the weakest claim,
he is ידא תחתונה. yada tachtona. So if the highest claim is
made, he has no defense basically. So that is if it increased
in value you go by the later date, even according to רבה.
Rabbah.
Because, right, because רבה Rabbah says...
Is there כפל kefel because it's like גזילה? gezeila?
There
is no כפל kefel because it's like גזילה. gezeila.
Yeah, because he took it and then he drank it, or he
was שליחות יד shlichus yad at a later point, the value had
increased, so at that point the value would be assessed, so that's
רבה's Rabbah saying. If it increased in value then the גזלן gazlan
loses out or the שומר shomer loses out.
So basically we're saying that this שליחות יד, shlichus yad, the שליח
יד sholiach yad is like a גזלן. gazlan. In other words, שליחות
יד
shlichus yad is certainly like a גזלן. gazlan. You took something.
Yeah, I know, because רבא Rava made it seem it's just by
a גזלן. gazlan.
Correct, he just said that. Well, that's exactly the point of this
סוגיא, sugya, to compare רבה's Rabbah שיטה shitta about a גזלן gazlan
to the משנה mishna which is about שליחות יד. shlichus yad. And
we're now saying, well it sounds like רבה's Rabbah position is like
בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, which is bad because we want אמוראים Amoraim
all to be within בית הלל. Beis Hillel.
And we should be distinguishing between a גזלן gazlan and a גנב,
ganav, right? It's not גניבה. geneiva.
It's not גניבה, geneiva, it's
a different—it's שליחות יד, shlichus yad, it's out in the open, so
to speak.
Well, I'm the שומר shomer and now I took it, that's גזילה,
gezeila, right? There was no sneaky, there was no hiding, there was
no...
Right, right, exactly, out in the open. As it happens, right. I
had the thing, I gave it to you and you just—you took
it—right, exactly, right,
right, so, aha, got it.
Right, okay. So בית שמאי... Beis Shamai... פליגי בחסר. pligi b'chaser. So
the מחלוקת machlokes בית שמאי Beis Shamai and בית הלל Beis Hillel
is about the principle of חסר, chaser, that is, like I was
alluding to earlier, בית שמאי סברי שליחות יד אינה צריכה חסרון. Beis
Shamai savri shlichus yad einah tzericha chisaron. בית שמאי Beis Shamai says
in order for שליחות יד shlichus yad to be the prohibition or
the crime of שליחות יד, shlichus yad, there does not need to
be any depreciation. It counts as שליחות יד shlichus yad before the
consumption or before the loss to the object.
וכי חסר ברשותא דידיה חסר. v'chi chaser b'reshusa didei chaser. And then
it depreciates in the value of the one who already stole it.
This gets back into the whole סוגיא sugya of קנייני גזילה. kinyanei
gezeila. קנין. kinyan. When the גזלן gazlan steals something, in a certain
sense the גזלן gazlan has ownership of it and then whatever appreciation
or depreciation in value that happens then will all happen in the
ownership of the גזלן. gazlan. ובית הלל סברי, u-Beis Hillel savri, but
בית הלל סברי שליחות יד צריכה חסרון. Beis Hillel savri shlichus yad
tzericha chisaron. In order for it to count as שליחות יד, shlichus
yad, the object must have a loss, it must lose a value
or some of it must be consumed. וכי חסר ברשותא דמרא חסר.
v'chi chaser b'reshusa d'marei chaser. So the first loss, that is when
it depreciates in value which triggers it being considered שליחות יד, shlichus
yad, will still take place while it is in the ownership of
the original owner.
So if I move a barrel of wine to get something, I've
not done anything according to בית הלל.
Beis Hillel. Correct, according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, according to that,
moving a barrel does not change its value, does not depreciate it
in value and therefore there would be no problem. We're going to
see an interesting case coming up on the top of מ"ד עמוד
א', mem dalet amud aleph, hopefully either today or tomorrow.
But according to בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, that wouldn't—that wouldn't be substantial
either?
Well, according to בית שמאי Beis Shamai though...
you
have to do some kind of stealing. So that's the question, does
moving it count? Probably not. So that's also a good question. אלא
הא דאמר רבה... Ela ha d'amar Rabbah...
Wait, so what is the case when בית שמאי... Beis Shamai...
You took from the barrel of wine, you took a glass of
wine and you drank it. בית הלל Beis Hillel would say, okay,
so that's שליחות יד shlichus yad because you drank it, but if
you take up a glass of wine and just put it on
the
counter—well, I didn't do anything, it was not חסר, chaser, so at
that case would not be שליחות יד, shlichus yad, for example.
So
according to בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, even a little tiny drop in
the cup in the barrel, thousands of your other wine... בית שמאי
Beis Shamai would say...
that's an interesting question, right. And then the question that comes up
in the גמרא Gemara next is—well later on—is going to be the
question of, well what if taking some of the wine out of
one barrel causes the rest of the wine to spoil? So in
that sense, well, you—even if you didn't drink the wine, but because
of your action you've depreciated. So some of those things come up.
I'm sorry, so according to בית שמאי Beis Shamai if I took
the glass of wine, put it on top of the barrel, so
I can always put it back in, so I'm still שומר?
shomer? No, according to בית שמאי, Beis Shamai,
that would be שליחות יד. shlichus yad. You did something inappropriate, you
were פושע poshea in your terms of שמירה. shmira. Okay, that's considered...
We're going to see the דרשות drashos coming up, it's going to
be—it's going to be clearer later on. Okay. ברשותא דמרא קא חסר.
B'reshusa d'marei ka chaser. אלא הא דאמר רבה, Ela ha d'amar Rabbah,
but what רבה Rabbah says, שליחות יד אינה צריכה חסרון, shlichus yad
einah tzericha chisaron, so רבה Rabbah seems to hold like בית שמאי.
Beis Shamai. לימא רבה דאמר כבית שמאי? leima Rabbah d'amar ke-Beis Shamai?
Can רבה Rabbah be holding like בית שמאי? Beis Shamai? So we
don't want to say that. So in other words, it's not that
בית שמאי Beis Shamai and בית הלל Beis Hillel actually hold these
positions, these are positions of other תנאים, Tannaim, they've been inserted into
בית שמאי Beis Shamai and בית הלל Beis Hillel and now we
said... No, no, no, we don't want to say that because we
don't want בית שמאי Beit Shammai to be the position that רבא
Rava ends up פוסק. paskening.
Wait, why do you say it's inserted? How do you know that?
Because I read the rest of the גמרא Gemara leading on and
on מ"ד עמוד א', Mem Dalet Amud Alef, the discussion is that
it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, am I
right?
That's a really sneaky answer.
It's a really sneaky answer. Sorry,
one sec.
Sorry, I accepted it completely.
Now I forget who it was who holds those positions, I'm sorry.
Okay, I think it was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, but I'm not sure. Really?
It's even a better answer to the קשיא kashya of how can
he hold like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai?
It's not really בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, exactly.
But we know it really is בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, but okay,
fine.
Right. אלא, Ella, yeah sure. שעת הוצאה. shaat hotza'ah. שעת הוצאה shaat
hotza'ah
according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. No, so it seems like the
working assumption we have right now is that שעת הוצאה, shaat hotza'ah,
הוצאה hotza'ah means הוצאה מרשות בעלים hotza'ah me'reshut be'alim when the object
is taken from the home of the owner and given to the
שומר, shomer, that's when the assessment would be.
Assessment according to שעת הוצאה, shaat hotza'ah, now that's בית הלל, Beit
Hillel, though.
No, בית הלל Beit Hillel says that, exactly.
But he holds בשנשתנה. be'she'nishtaneh.
That's about שליחות יד shlichut yad in general, that שליחות יד shlichut
yad in order for it to be considered שליחות יד shlichut yad
must have a loss in value, depreciation. That's not about when you
assess the depreciation, who pays based on what. That was רבא's Rava
point, right? רבא Rava said we calculate it based on that the
מחלוקת machloket is only in a case of חסר. chasir. If the
loss, if it lost money, like the wine, I gave a barrel
of wine at that time and then it goes down, so בית
הלל Beit Hillel will say, well you go by the time it
left the owner's house. And בית שמאי Beit Shammai will say you
go by whichever one the שומר shomer has to pay more, right?
So then they would be agreeing.
That's a bit tricky. But I think
something got a little bit mixed up,
or okay, sorry.
We'll keep going. Okay. דאמר רבא, de'amar Rava, שליחות יד אינה צריכה
חסרון, shlichut yad eina tzericha chisaron, לימא רבא דאמר כבית שמאי? leima
Rava de'amar ke'Beit Shammai? אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, Ella hacha be'mai askinan,
this is what we're talking about. So now a third possibility, third
attempt to understand what the מחלוקת machloket בית שמאי Beit Shammai and
בית הלל Beit Hillel is, כגון שטלטלה להביא עליה גוזל. k'gon she'tiltela
le'havi aleha gozal. So he used it as a ladder to go
reach your doves in the dovecote. ובשואל שלא מדעת קמיפלגי. u've'sho'el she'lo
mi'da'at ka'miphalgi.
They have a מחלוקת machloket about שואל שלא מדעת, sho'el she'lo mi'da'at,
that is, I'm a שומר shomer for this object, I want to
use it for some use that's not going to cause any damage.
I'm going to stand on top of the wine barrel, fine. So
it's שואל שלא מדעת, sho'el she'lo mi'da'at, I'm borrowing it without permission.
So בית שמאי סברי שואל שלא מדעת גזלן הוי, Beit Shammai savri
sho'el she'lo mi'da'at gazlan havei, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says a שואל
שלא מדעת sho'el she'lo mi'da'at is like a גזלן gazlan and therefore
וכי חסר ברשותיה דידיה חסר ve'chi chasir birshutei didei chasir because at
that time that I stood on it, when I was borrowing it
without permission, then I have stolen it. And then once it depreciates
in value, it depreciates in value in the גזלן's gazlan רשות, reshut,
so he has to pay a higher value. בית הלל סברי שואל
שלא מדעת שואל הוי. Beit Hillel savri sho'el she'lo mi'da'at sho'el havei.
בית הלל Beit Hillel says borrowing something without permission is categorized
as borrowing. וכי חסר ברשותיה דמאריה חסר ve'chi chasir birshutei de'marei chasir
and therefore if the value goes down once he borrowed it, still
it will go down in the value, in the ownership of its
owner and therefore the שומר shomer will only have to pay the
lower value. Okay. אלא הא דאמר רבא, Ella had'amar Rava, שואל שלא
מדעת לרבנן גזלן הוי, sho'el she'lo mi'da'at le'rabbanan gazlan havei, but רבא
Rava told us later that שואל שלא מדעת sho'el she'lo mi'da'at we
פוסק pasken is like a גזלן. gazlan. So הווה לימא רבא כדברי
בית שמאי? hava leima Rava ke'divrei Beit Shammai? Does רבא Rava
say like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? אלא הכא בשבח של גזילה קמיפלגי.
Ella hacha be'shevach shel gezeila ka'miphalgi. Fourth attempt. So we had three
attempts, the first one was that רבא, Rava, we said does רבא
Rava hold like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? Then we had two cases
of does רבא Rava hold like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? So now
we have a fourth attempt. I think it's interesting how the numbers
work out, the סוגיא sugaya is kind of unusual that there are
four cases.
Okay, we're talking about שבח של גזילה, shevach shel gezeila, the, that
is, I stole a sheep and the sheep has wool and the
wool kept growing. So that's the שבח shevach of a גזילה, gezeila,
that is when you steal a sheep, who owns the wool that
grew during the time that the animal was stolen?
As you have it in your possession and it grows.
Exactly. So בית שמאי סברי שבח גזילה דניגזל הוי. Beit Shammai savri
shevach gezeila de'nigzal havei.
According to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, the growth of the wool belongs
to the original owner. ובית הלל סברי שבח גזילה דגזלן הוי, u'veit
Hillel savri shevach gezeila de'gazlan havei, but בית הלל Beit Hillel says
once you stole it, the liability kicks in at the time of
the theft and then if the wool kept growing, that actually belongs
to the גזלן. gazlan. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי, u'v'iplugta de'hani tana'ei,
and בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל Beit Hillel are aligned
with another מחלוקת תנאים, machloket Tannaim, דתניא הגוזל את הרחל, גזזה וילדה,
משלם אותה ואת גיזותיה ואת ולדותיה דברי רבי מאיר. de'tanya hagozel et
harachel, gezaza ve'yalda, meshalem otah ve'et gizoteha ve'et veladoteha divrei Rabbi Meir.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
like what we said was בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, that you have
to pay back everything, including the baby sheep, including the wool. Lambs,
yes, that's the word for it. רבי יהודה אומר גזילה חוזרת כעינה.
Rabbi Yehuda omer gezeila chozeret ke'einah. According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
you only give it back like what it was at the time
it was stolen. So you shear back the wool and the גזלן
gazlan can keep it, you keep the lambs, whatever else. דייקא נמי
דקתני, dayka nami de'katani, so we can say this is also precise
reading of our משנה, mishna, בית שמאי
אומרים ילקה בחסר
ויתר.
Beit Shammai omrim yilke
be'chasir ve'yater. חסר ויתר chasir ve'yater does not sound like that it
was
external, like lambs.
No, it does sound like that. It doesn't sound like fluctuations in
the market value. בית הלל אומרים Beis Hillel omrim כשעת הוצאה, ke'sha'as
hotza'ah, שמע מינה. shma mina. It sounds like the object itself grew
or shrank, not that the market fluctuated. And therefore that explanation, that
is really this מחלוקת machlokes is not about whether the price of
wine has gone up or down, but whether only in case something
that actually can produce on its own, a chicken, a sheep, a
something, or I stole a tree and the tree, you know, קרקע
נגזלת, karka nigzela, stole a plant in a flowerpot and the plant
kept growing or something like that, you only return it back to
what it was at the time you stole it.
Yes? To clarify for me just for a second. So according to
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, שואל
שלא מדעת shoel shelo midaas is a שואל. shoel. But what does
that mean? In other words, I've borrowed something from you and I
can use it in some way that you might not have intended
me to use?
Well, obviously a שואל, shoel, if something breaks or if something is
stolen or if something gets lost, well then a שואל shoel will
be חייב. chayav. א גזלן A gazlan is also חייב chayav for
those things. So it's not about the liability, but it is about
whether or not there was that
transfer of ownership. That is, a גזלן gazlan we have a stronger
sense that there are קניני גזילה, kinyanei gezeilah, that is, at the
moment of theft, the גזלן gazlan in some sense owns it and
has a liability to pay back its value. Therefore the גזלן gazlan
has more control over the object. But a שואל, shoel, as much
as the ראשונים Rishonim try to put a שואל shoel very similar
to a גזלן gazlan and say a שואל shoel also in some
sense really owns the object that he's borrowed.
Right. Like בית הלל Beis Hillel says שואל שלא מדעת, shoel shelo
midaas, in other words I've been I've been קונה koneh this as
a שואל shoel in some way even though you didn't.
Well but and that's the question. If I borrow someone's bicycle, well
why am I חייב באונס? chayav b'ones? Right? So the suggestion many
ראשונים Rishonim give why a שואל shoel is חייב באונסין chayav b'onsim
is because the שואל shoel kind of really owns it. The problem
is then a שואל shoel is basically the same as a גזלן
gazlan in terms of liability or in terms of ownership. That is,
a שואל, shoel, I bought the bicycle and now I have to
give it back at the end of the terms of the lease.
But that is basically the same as a גזלן gazlan in terms
of how we would conceptualize this. So then the מחלוקת machlokes about
שואל שלא מדעת, shoel shelo midaas, how do you think about it?
Well part of it is is שואל שלא מדעת shoel shelo midaas
a crime or not? That is, borrowing someone's thing and not without
them knowing about it. Is that really like stealing it or is
it really like, well, I'm just borrowing it? And he probably would
have said yes.
And נפקא מינא? nafka mina?
And נפקא מינא nafka mina we see a case here like this,
like when do you assess the value of the object in terms
of increase or decrease in value, things like that.
Or when it broke?
Right and things like that and becomes a broader a broader case.
Obviously like I was saying, it gets to be very fine distinction
because the liabilities are so similar. Okay, רבי עקיבא אומר כשעת התביעה.
Rabbi Akiva omer ke'sha'as hatviah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says we assess
it based what?
In this case with the שואל, shoel,
the גזלן gazlan is responsible, but isn't the שומר shomer responsible if
it's stolen? So that's exactly the question. שומר חינם A shomer chinam
is פטור patur if it was stolen. שומר שכר A shomer sachar
is פטור patur if it was stolen by armed robbers.
But if it's stolen other means, he's חייב. chayav.
Exactly, for sure, שומר שכר. shomer sachar. So why
do we put the חיוב chiyuv on the גזלן gazlan that the
שומר שכר shomer sachar is חייב? chayav? So we're talking about two
different cases. One is a case where the שומר shomer stole it
himself. That's שליחות יד. shelichus yad. And one is a case a
person had some object and someone else came and stole it. So
we're not right now talking about a case where it was stolen
from a שומר, shomer, but two parallel cases, one with a גזלן
gazlan and one with a שואל. shoel.
What about the case where the שומר shomer himself stole?
Exactly, שליחות יד. shelichus yad. So that's the שומר shomer case. שומר
A shomer went and misappropriated the פקדון pikadon in some way, שליחות
יד. shelichus yad. That's the conclusion of this פרק. perek. The next
משנה Mishnah is going to be about that as well. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva omer כשעת התביעה.
ki-sh'as ha-tvi'ah. The assessment of the value of the object will go
by the time of the court case. Okay, that's a reasonable reasonable
position it seems. Okay, so אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי
עקיבא. amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halachah k'Rabbi Akiva. According to שמואל
Shmuel and we know we follow שמואל בדיני Shmuel bedinei. so it
sounds like שמואל Shmuel says הלכה halachah is like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. מודה רבי עקיבא במקום שיש עדים. Modeh Rabbi Akiva b'makom sheyesh
eidim. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agrees to to whom? To בית
הלל Beis Hillel maybe? Yes.
Can we just go back for a second? I wasn't paying attention.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says כשעת התביעה. ke'sha'as hatviah. Did we explain
what that meant?
We're doing it right now. So שעת התביעה sha'as hatviah sounds like
the time the claim is made in court.
That's what we would normally think תביעה tviah means. That establishes what
value the object should be assessed at at that time.
So we saw the בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, בית הלל. Beis Hillel.
בית שמאי Beis Shammai said the שואל shoel always loses out, he
always has the highest claim put against him whether it went up
and down in value. בית הלל Beis Hillel said it goes by
the initial value either way. We saw that that ended up being
slogged onto a very small case, that is a case of things
which naturally appreciate in value or depreciate in value but not about
market fluctuations. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it'll be assessed based
on the time of the court case, the latest time basically.
Initial value when it was
taken? When it
was taken out of the owner's.
That
would be what we thought הוצאה hotza'ah means, right?
As opposed to when it was spent or broken.
Exactly. Okay, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says כשעת התביעה, keshas hatviah, and שמואל Shmuel said the הלכה halacha
should be like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. ומודה רבי עקיבא במקום שיש
עדים, Umodeh Rabbi Akiva bimkom sheyesh edim, but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
agrees at a time that there are witnesses. So what does that
mean? So we'll have to find out. So מאי טעמא? mai tama?
דאמר קרא, לאשר הוא לו יתננו ביום אשמתו. da'amar kra la'asher hu
lo yitnenu beyom ashmato, The פסוק pasuk says someone who has committed
שליחות יד shlichus yad has stolen the the
deposited object, so to whom it is his יתננו, yitnenu, he has
to give it to him ביום אשמתו beyom ashmato on the day
of his sin. וכיון דאיכא עדים, Vechivan de'ika edim, the fact that
there are witnesses מההיא שעתא דאיחייב ליה אשמה, me'hahi shata de'ichayav leh
ashma, דאיחייב ליה אשמה. de'ichayav leh ashma.
So at that time, the time that the witnesses see you stealing
it, that is the time that you should have to pay the
crime. That is according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva we should go
by the time of the court case, but if there are witnesses
who saw him stealing it, then it would go by the time
that he actually stole it according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So
אמר ליה בר אושעיא לרב יהודה, amar leh bar Oshaya le'Rav Yehuda,
so בר אושעיא bar Oshaya said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, רבי,
אתה אומר כן? Rebbi, atah omer ken? You're really going to say
this? So he's challenging רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. כי הכי אמר רב
אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, ki hachi amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan,
so according to רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan opinion, it's interesting, it's kind
of we have a מחלוקת machlokes between רב יהודה Rav Yehuda quoting
שמואל Shmuel in בבל Bavel and we have
רב אסי Rav Assi quoting רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said חלוק היה רבי עקיבא אפילו
במקום שיש עדים. Chaluk hayah Rabbi Akiva afilu bimkom sheyesh edim. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagreed with בית הלל Beis Hillel even if there
are witnesses. That is it always goes by the time of the
court case and not by the time that the witnesses saw it.
מאי טעמא? mai tama? דאמר קרא da'amar kra, לאשר הוא לו יתננו
ביום אשמתו, la'asher hu lo yitnenu beyom ashmato. ובית דין הוא דקמחייבי
ליה אשמה. uveish din hu de'kamachayvei leh ashma. It's not the witnesses
who make you a criminal, it's the court who makes you a
criminal. That's a fascinating distinction when we think about criminal law in
הלכה. halacha. What's the role of the court? Is the court just
there to assess the facts and to say well whatever the witnesses
saw and proved that's what happened and therefore you get this sentence,
you get from that time, or is it the court who creates
the legal reality of the crime by judging the case? So obviously
נפקא מינה nafka mina is well what if a person never goes
to court for something? So if even if witnesses saw it but
they never have a court case, was that person הלכתית halachically considered
to be a criminal for all those kind of things? You know,
you can't trust their witnesses and you can't let them borrow money
and lend money and things like that? So it becomes very interesting.
The time is a significant component in a criminal event. Of course.
Murder occurs the time it occurs, not when the court says it
occurs. But it's not when the court says murder occurred six months
later.
Right, but what creates the criminality, the אשמה, ashma, the guilt, the
personal sense of being a criminal in a human sense? Is that
at the time of the court case or at the time of
the crime?
Certainly a fascinating psychological discussion as well, but not for now. Okay,
אמר רבי זירא לרבי אבא בר פפא, amar Rabbi Zeira le'Rabbi Abba
bar Pappa, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said to רבי אבא בר
פפא, Rabbi Abba bar Pappa, כי אזלת להתם אקיף אסולמא דצור, ki
azlat le'hasam akif asulma de'Tzur, when you go there go to the
staircase of צור Tzur ועול לגבי דרבי יעקב בר אידי ובעי מיניה,
ve'ol legabei de'Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi uva'ei minei, and go to רבי
יעקב בר אידי Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi and ask him אי שמיע
ליה דרבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי עקיבא או אין הלכה כרבי עקיבא, ei
shemia leh de'Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke'Rabbi Akiva o ein halacha ke'Rabbi Akiva,
go ask him if he heard from רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan whether
the הלכה halacha is like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or not. אמר
ליה, amar leh, he said to him, question who said to whom,
is it רבי יעקב בר אידי Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi who said
it or is it the person who went and came back to
רבי זירא... Rabbi Zeira... to
רבי אבא בר פפא, Rabbi Abba bar Pappa, sorry. אמר ליה, amar
leh, he said הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, this
is what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, הלכה כרבי עקיבא לעולם. halacha
ke'Rabbi Akiva le'olam.
The הלכה halacha is always like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or will
always be like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or something. So מאי לעולם?
mai le'olam? What does it mean forever? אמר רב אשי, amar Rav
Ashi, שלא תאמר הני מילי היכא דליכא עדים, she'lo tomar hanei milei
heicha de'leika edim, that we this משנה mishnah is only in a
case of מחלוקת machlokes when there are no witnesses. אבל היכא דאיכא
עדים לא, aval heicha de'ika edim lo, but the משנה mishnah does
not apply when there are witnesses. In other words, and this seemingly
confirms רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagrees
with בית הלל Beis Hillel even when there are witnesses. That is
that the court creates the status and the court, the time of
the court case is when we assess the value. ואינמי דאהדרה לדוכתא
ואיטברה לאפוקי מדרבי ישמעאל, ve'inami de'ahadrah le'duchta ve'itbarah le'afokei mi'de'Rabbi Yishmael, and
the fact that he said that when it if it goes back
and it breaks that comes to contradict the opinion of רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael דאמר לא בעינן דעת בעלים, de'amar lo beinan da'as be'alim,
that we don't require that the owners be aware of it, קא
משמע לן דבעינן דעת בעלים, ka mashma lan de'beinan da'as be'alim, and
that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position comes to exclude רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says we do need the awareness
of the owner. That is the by the time the court case
obviously the owner will be aware of it. ורבא אמר הלכה כבית
הלל. ve'Rava amar halacha ke'Beis Hillel. So now it's very interesting, we
have this whole back and forth about what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
thinks because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
but then רבא Rava referencing back to רב יהודה... Rav Yehuda... who
is referencing back to שמואל, Shmuel בבלי Bavli tradition says הלכה Halakha
is like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So this is an interesting סוגיא
sugya just for in terms of כללי הפסק, klalei hapsak, how do
we follow הלכה? Halakha? We have משניות. mishnayos. They have a בית
הלל, Beis Hillel, which is usually להלכה. lehalakha. We have רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, who is usually להלכה. lehalakha. We have the שקלא וטריא
shakla vetarya of the גמרא Gemara seems to be very interested in
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but nonetheless, the rules of פסק, psak, רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan is
that is that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva should be the הלכה, halakha,
exactly. So the discussion of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would incline us
to think the הלכה halakha could be like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
And if you look in רש"י, Rashi, and it's the same as
in the רי"ף, Rif, it's interesting, it's almost like רש"י's Rashi quoting
the רי"ף, Rif, but רש"י Rashi probably didn't have the רי"ף. Rif.
רש"י Rashi says, כשעת גזילה ואנן כרבא עבדינן, kishe'at gezeila ve'anan keRava
avidnan, we hold like רבא, Rava, דהוה ליה בתרא. dehavei lei batra.
So we follow the general principle הלכה כבתרא. halakha kebatra. The הלכה
halakha follows the latest opinion. The latest אמורא Amora mentioned here in
this סוגיא sugya is רבא. Rava. So רבא Rava says הלכה halakha
is like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So that's what you go by.
Yes. Oh, sorry, like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. My mistake. Sorry.
So how is בית הלל Beis Hillel different from עקיבא? Akiva?
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and בית הלל Beis Hillel had a
מחלוקת, machlokes, remember in the משנה. mishna. בית הלל Beis Hillel said
you go by the initial time. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you
go by the court case. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says הלכה halakha
is like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even if there are witnesses, even
if there aren't witnesses. And רבא Rava says based on שמואל Shmuel,
says הלכה halakha should be like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. בית שמאי.
Beis Shammai.
בית שמאי Beis Shammai we never hold like.
So I want to know what's the difference between the other two.
So בית שמאי Beis Shammai was interesting because it was variable. בית
שמאי's Beis Shammai position was that the שומר shomer who was שולח
בו יד sholeach bo yad always loses out. If the value goes
up, then he has to pay the higher value. If the value
goes down, he still has to pay the initial value when it
was higher. Rabbi Dubi, you had a question?
I do. So on this question of השמה hashama when that legal
reality kicks in. So the סוגיא sugya says רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
said to אבא בר פפא, Abba bar Pappa, right, go to go
to ask רבי יעקב בר אידי, Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi, right? Yes.
So it says אקיף אקילא דצור. akif akila deTzur. Yes. So is
רש"י's Rashi point on אקיף akif that he intentionally made him go
the long way around and not take a shortcut? Is there some
significance to that? He says אקיף akif means like you take the
long way. Do you see that?
Yeah, I'm not sure what הלכתי halakhic significance there is because כל
מקום שהלך דרך ארוכה במקום שיש קצרה מקיף הוא. kol makom shehalach
derech aruka bemakom sheyesh ketzara makif hu. He's encircling, encircling.
He wants to think about it on the way. Like is there
some...
I don't know, there's something there.
There's something there, right?
רש"י's Rashi like clearly bothered by the word מקיף, makif, to encircle
the staircase of צור. Tzur. I don't know what what the topography
of צור Tzur is like and what how many staircases there were.
Yeah, I don't know. רש"י Rashi clearly has some kind of a
some kind
of a problem with that.
He sent his colleague or student to go ask a שאלה shaila
far away in a different town in a different city and something's
bothering him. Something's bothering רש"י Rashi for sure. What's bothering רש"י? Rashi?
Let's see.
בית הלל Beis Hillel and עקיבא Akiva weren't contemporaries. Exactly.
We had an earlier מחלוקת machlokes בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית
הלל Beis Hillel and then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva much later has
a different opinion, but they're all codified in a משנה mishna all
three. So that's the other question is like how do we sort
of flatten those strata when we're analyzing it להלכה lehalakha and we
say okay, רבא Rava told me it's like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has this פסוק, pasuk, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
has what... sorry, רבא Rava says like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Sorry.
So we don't have any motivation for why רבא Rava thinks the
הלכה halakha is like בית הלל Beis Hillel except that what did
we say? שמואל Shmuel said, right? So we follow שמואל Shmuel בדיני.
b'dini So שמואל Shmuel just sort of told us okay, הלכה halakha
is like בית הלל, Beis Hillel, but we don't have any argumentation
or or justification for that פסק. psak. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan seems
to go through this whole thing to analyze רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
position. It's very interesting. I'm sure there's extended discussion of this.
Well, he's brought into this, he's talkatively...
Well, he's brought in because in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they obviously
פסקן pasken like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
פסקן pasken like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Everyone said oh, what did
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say? Did he say רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
in this case or even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in this other
case? So obviously in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the פסק psak was
like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And in בבל Bavel they said we
want to פסקן pasken like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. It becomes very
interesting in terms of כללי הפסק, klalei hapsak, how do you
how do you take from the גמרא?
Gemara? Regardless of the witnesses?
According to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan we... according רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says you follow רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva whether or not there are
witnesses. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it always goes by the court
case, not by the witnesses. Right. And that was רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan against the opinion of רבי אושעיא רבי יהודה. Rabbi Oshaya Rabbi
Yehuda.
And הלל Hillel then would hold regardless of witnesses as well, right?
Right. Well, they didn't have anything to do with the witnesses question
exactly.
Because saying if he does hold we go by the witnesses he'd
be like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. That wasn't clear.
Well no, not like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. He would go by
the time of the witnesses seeing it. That's what he said. Not
like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. רבי
עקיבא's
Rabbi
Akiva
position according to רבי יעקב בר אידי, Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi,
according to רבי
אושעיא רבי יהודה Rabbi Oshaya Rabbi Yehuda says it goes by the
time of the witnesses, and according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan quoted
by רב אסי, Rav Assi, it would go by even whether or
not there were witnesses, right?
לעולם, le'olam, that's לעולם, le'olam,
right, forever.
But of course that line also becomes interesting, הלכה כרבי עקיבא... halakha
keRabbi Akiva... But of course that line also becomes interesting, הלכה כרבי
עקיבא לעולם, halakha k'Rabbi Akiva le'olam, well maybe the הלכה halakha should
always be like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva from the משנה. mishnah. So
we know there's a rule, רבי עקיבא מחברו, Rabbi Akiva mechaveiro, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva against one other תנא, tanna, the הלכה halakha should
follow רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva but not against חביריו, chaveirav, against a
majority רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva we don't follow.
But not against הלל Hillel either, who was...
Well that's an interesting question. But it's בית הלל. Beit Hillel. בית
הלל Beit Hillel is a majority, so maybe this is going back
to how do we understand that? Is that the opinion of הלל
Hillel or the opinion of בית הלל? Beit Hillel? Let's see if
we can do a little bit more to the next דף daf
so we could maybe try to finish up the פרק. perek. The
משנה mishnah says החושב לשלוח יד בפיקדון. hachochev lishlo'ach yad bepikadon. Someone
who intends to be שלוח יד, shole'ach yad, that is someone who
intends to steal from the פיקדון, pikadon, has not done so yet.
בית שמאי אומרים חייב. Beit Shammai omrim chayav. From the time you
have the thought, it sounds like you become חייב. chayav. בית הלל
אומרים אינו חייב עד שישלח בו יד. Beit Hillel omrim eino chayav
ad sheyishlach bo yad. Minority report, right?
There you go.
You had the idea, you because at that point you violated your
terms of שמירה shmira because as soon as you had the intention
to do it, now you're not a שומר shomer anymore because the
fact that you're going to allow someone to steal from it means
that you're not a שומר. shomer. So that's kind of the conceptual
sense of בית שמאי Beit Shammai that you could have a mental
crime, it's very interesting. בית הלל Beit Hillel says no, you have
to... it has to be when you actually put your hand on
it to take it, שנאמר, shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk says אם לא
שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו. im lo shalach yado bimlechet rei'ehu. If he
takes an oath, a שומר shomer has to take שבועת השומרים, shvu'at
hashomrim, שבועת השומרים shvu'at hashomrim to say I didn't steal it.
The פסוק pasuk by שבועת השומרים shvu'at hashomrim says I didn't put
my hand on my friend's object.
The first רש"י Rashi
is good on the שלח בו
יד. shalach bo yad. Yeah. What's it say?
It says אומר לפני עדים אקחנה לעצמי ואשתמש בה. omer lifnei eidim
ekachena le'atzmi ve'eshtamesh bah.
Oh that's very interesting. To solidify, right, not to just think it.
So רש"י Rashi is obviously uncomfortable with the plain פשט pshat of
you could have a mental crime, which is obviously Rabbi Dov's point,
which is how can you have a mental crime? There's no such
thing in הלכה. halakha. Yeah David?
I also think he says you have to have... it has to
be explained with witnesses.
According to רש"י Rashi that would be the case. But according to
the plain reading of the משנה mishnah no. Obviously רש"י Rashi inserts
that because the plain reading of the משנה mishnah would be very
unusual. Okay.
So but it does, for instance in the case of divorce... right.
One thinks that he's going to divorce his
wife...
has certain implications.
There's certain implications, becomes a very complicated extended
סוגיא. sugya. There you go. Exactly. So I just didn't want to
get so into it but yeah, good point. Okay, עד שישלח בו
יד, ad sheyishlach bo yad,
because the פסוק pasuk says אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו. im
lo shalach yado bimlechet rei'ehu. הטה את החבית, hita et hachavit, if
he tilted the barrel ונטל הימנה רביעית, venatal heimena revi'it, and he
took one glass of wine out ונשברה, venishbera, and then it broke,
אינו משלם אלא רביעית. eino meshalem ela revi'it.
You only have to pay back
one wine glass's worth of wine. הגביהה, higbi'ah, if he raised up
the whole barrel ונטל הימנה רביעית, venatal heimena revi'it, and then took
one glass of wine ונשברה, venishbera, and it broke, משלם דמי כולה,
meshalem dmei kullah, because he lifted up the whole barrel at once.
We're going to see the justification for that in the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says מנהני מילי, man hani milei, how do we
know that there's this מחלוקת machloket between בית שמאי ובית הלל Beit
Shammai u'Beit Hillel about whether or not שליחות יד shlichut yad is
when you put your hand on it or not? So דתנו רבנן,
detanu rabanan, we have a ברייתא, braita, על כל דבר פשע al
kol dvar pasha בית שמאי אומרים מלמד שחייב על המחשבה כמעשה. Beit
Shammai omrim melamed shechayav al hamachshava kema'aseh. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
you're liable even for a mental crime it sounds like, not even
until you've done the thing. ובית הלל אומרים אינו חייב עד שישלח
בו יד. u'Beit Hillel omrim eino chayav ad sheyishlach bo yad. בית
הלל Beit Hillel says you have to actually do the action. שנאמר
אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו. shene'emar im lo shalach yado bimlechet
rei'ehu. You didn't put your hand on it so you're not guilty.
אמרו להן בית שמאי לבית הלל, amru lahen Beit Shammai le'Beit Hillel,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai responds והלא כבר נאמר על כל דבר פשע,
vahalo kvar ne'emar al kol dvar pasha, for every crime. For every
crime would include even a mental crime. אמרו להן בית הלל לבית
שמאי, amru lahen Beit Hillel le'Beit Shammai, בית הלל Beit Hillel responds
והלא כבר נאמר אם לא שלח ידו במלאכת רעהו. vahalo kvar ne'emar
im lo shalach yado bimlechet rei'ehu. But the פסוק pasuk is very
clear that the crime in reference is being referenced is actually trying
to steal it. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר על כל דבר פשע?
im ken mah talmud lomar al kol dvar pasha? So what does
it mean every crime? שיכול אין לי אלא הוא. sheyachol ein li
ela hu. So I would only think that it's if the person,
the שומר, shomer, tried to steal it himself. אמר לעבדו ולשלוחו מניין?
amar le'avdo u'lishlucho minayin?
What if he tells someone else to steal it, his slave or
his representative, some other kind of שליח? shaliach? תלמוד לומר על כל
דבר פשע. talmud lomar al kol dvar pasha. That's what בית הלל
Beit Hillel does with the principle of על כל דבר פשע. al
kol dvar pasha. And if we remember back to when we learned
מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin in the second פרק, perek, we know that
שליחות יד shlichut yad along with טביחה ומכירה tivicha u'mechira and מעילה
me'ila is one of the three exceptions to the principle אין שליח
לדבר עבירה. ein shaliach lidvar aveira. Here we see that שליחות יד
shlichut yad according to בית הלל Beit Hillel at least, there is
שליח לדבר עבירה. shaliach lidvar aveira. If I ask someone else to
steal this פיקדון pikadon that I'm watching, then I am responsible, not
the שליח shaliach or both of us are responsible. Okay. הטה את
החבית, hita et hachavit, if you tilted the barrel to get the
glass of wine. אמר רבה לא שנו אלא נשברה. amar Rabba lo
shanu ela nishbera. They didn't teach this הלכה halakha except in the
case where the barrel broke. אבל החמיצה משלם את כולה. aval hachmitza
meshalem et kullah. If the wine in the barrel went bad, soured,
even if you only tilted the barrel or took it from the
spout, you're liable. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? גירי דידיה הוא דאהני ליה,
girei dideyhu de'ahani leh, because your own arrow is the reason why
that happened. That is what happened? I took a glass of wine
out of the barrel, now there's more air space at the top
and the wine will oxidize.
As the breaking of the barrel, there's something between your action and
the breaking. Exactly.
Right. The breaking and the breaking was אונס, ones, the barrel just
broke on its own, but here the חימוץ chimutz happened because I
opened up the air space. So exactly. So Rava distinguishes between those
kind of cases. Okay. הגביה, higbi'ah, if you raised up the barrel,
ונטל הימנה, venatal mimena, and you took the wine out. So אמר
שמואל, amar Shmuel, לא נטל נטל ממש, lo natal natal mamash, נטל
natal to take the glass of wine doesn't mean you have to
have taken, אלא כיון שהגביה ליטול, ella keivan shehigbi'ah litol, even when
he raised it up to take the wine, אף על פי שלא
נטל, af al pi shelo natal, so even if you didn't take
the wine yet. That is at the time you lift up the
whole barrel, that's when you become liable. לימא קסבר שמואל שליחות יד
אינה צריכה חסרון, lima kasavar Shmuel shlichut yad eina tzericha chisaron, maybe
Shmuel is the one who holds that שליחות יד shlichut yad does
not require a loss in value, because what happened? You lifted up
the whole barrel, so that's שליחות יד shlichut yad even if you
didn't take a glass of wine. So this לימא lima would be
rejected. אמרי לא, amrei lo, שאני הכא דניחא ליה דתהוי החבית כולה
בסיס להרביעית. shani hacha denicha lei dteihavei hachavis kulla basis leharvi'it. No,
Shmuel only holds that because when you lifted up the barrel, you
wanted the entire ten gallons of wine to be a בסיס basis
to support the glass of wine, רביעית revi'it of wine floating on
top, because that's what I'm going to take when I take it
out with the glass of wine. And that's why he actually had
some intention about it, not just that because the חסרון chisaron will
still be when you take the wine. So even though you didn't
take it yet, your intention was to take it in the future
and you wanted the wine to support it, that's why. איבעיא ליה
לרב אשי, ibaiya lei leRav Ashi, הגביה ארנקי, higbi'ah arneki, what if
you lifted up a wallet, ליטול הימנה דינר, litol mimena dinar, to
take one coin out of the wallet? So מהו? mahu? חמרא הוא
דלא מנטר, chamra hu dlo mintar, so wine is the one that
is sort of is not well contained or well guarded inside inside
the jar, אלא
אגב חמרא, ella agav chamra, but the wine floats on top of
the other wine, and that's why Shmuel would say, well, I need
the rest of the wine to support the wine on top in
order to be able to take it out easily. And therefore Shmuel,
that's why the Mishnah holds the הלכה halacha that if when you
lifted it up, that's when you become חייב. chayav. But for a
wallet, אבל זוזא מנטר, aval zuza mintar, but a coin is well
guarded in the wallet whether it's on top or on the bottom,
it's by the ארנקי, arneki, it's not by the wine. או דלמא
שאני נטירותא דארנקי מנטירותא דדינר, o dilma shani netiruta de'arneki minetiruta dedinar,
they have different level of guardedness in their containers. That is the
container, they're different. So תיקו. teiku. Basically, the wallet with the coin,
do we think that the other money in the wallet is supporting
the coin in such a way that there's a benefit there? And
therefore if you lift up the wallet only to take the top
coin, you still got a benefit from the other coins. And that's
comparable and therefore if you lifted up the whole wallet rather than
just tilting it to knock out the top coin, that that would
be שליחות יד shlichut yad on the entire wallet or no? It's
left unresolved and we can say הדרן עלך המפקיד hadran alach HaMafkid
and we'll pick up tomorrow with פרק הזהב. Perek HaZahav.